[Music]
Hello. Good evening. Good day,
everybody. And welcome back to the Ask
Abhijit Show. Today we're doing episode
295. We're going to talk about history.
I'm going to take questions that you all
have asked in the comments.
But before we do that, let me greet
as many of you as I can in the next
couple of minutes. Who's there on the
live stream, on the live chat? I'm a
painter, Dhruv Duriya, Sentin SP.
Samriddhi Mishra, Jai Shri Ram,
Satellite.
Welcome. Vladimir Putin. Ritvik
Sardesai, Ashwini, I'm a painter, Mystic
Escape, The Great Gatsby, Stanzin
Dorjee, Abhinay Singh, Mr. Saxena, God
Emperor Doom, Critical Thinker.
Ayush Singh.
Uh who else do we have? The Great
Gatsby, Bruce Wayne, Ansh Ashwini,
Mayank Choudhary, Anonymous Scientist,
Moswar.
Uh Abhi Chandel 05, Alex Mayank
Choudhary.
Uh injured soccer player from
Richmond Hill, Ontario, Canada. I hope
your injury gets well and you you deal
with
it it goes away as soon as as possible.
Uh Uday Kiran, Geopolitical Dubai, good
evening from Indore as always. Uh Atman
Moksha, Wise Idiot.
Beneath Como estas? Como estas? Very
well, sir. Very well.
Uh Priyanshi Sood, Reinhard Moses.
Riser.
Thanks.
Excuse me.
Ayush Singh 439, hello. Ajinkya Pawar,
The Great Gatsby, Shanks evening.
God Emperor Doom, Ayush Singh.
Amisha Mishra, hello.
Uh Vladimir Putin, once again, hello.
Manisha Cardoso, Namaste. Krishna
Raghunath from the Suriname,
Netherlands, hello. Baron Zemo.
Beneath.
Um
Samriddhi Mishra, hello.
Uh Ritvik Sardesai, once again, KS Anime
Edits, hello. Beneath, Gagan Arora.
IPK underscore 100 1 1S Keshav Tyagi,
thank you.
Uh Netizen.
Pratik Vora, Shashank Kaushik, Sujit
Kundu, Shanks.
Uh
Rinky Choudhary, Random Skull, good to
see you, sir. Rohan Jadhavkar.
Ajinkya Pawar, Gagan Arora.
A and R Studios, that is Ansh.
Uh
Is it cold over here? Yeah, it's kind of
cold.
Ken Pax Shield Kunal Bind, yes, thank
you.
Ken Untriggered 69, Tanmay, Freedom from
Outcome from Canada.
Uh
and everyone else. Okay.
So,
Ankita is here and everyone else. So,
I'm going to take questions from
from the comments that you've all that
you've asked in the comments. Manchu
Kalam, Rakesh Mishra, Ajinkya Pawar.
All right. So, let's get going with the
questions. I'm not taking questions from
the live chat right now. At the end, if
there's time, I'll take some questions
from the live chat.
But let's get going with the questions
for for this episode. What's the first
question? It's I'm going to take
questions about history, world history,
Indian history, and that's about it.
So,
The first question is by Swapnil Mishra.
What exactly was life like in the now
submerged landmass that once connected
Britain to continental Europe before it
disappeared beneath the North Sea?
There used to be a landmass that
connected Britain
to continental Europe
until about roughly 10,000 years before
today.
Uh during the last last ice age.
So, what is today Britain, those
islands, it was once a peninsula of
Europe. It was connected to the mainland
of Europe. Just like at that time, Sri
Lanka,
present-day Sri Lanka, which is an
island, was at that time, same time, it
was connected to mainland India. It was
an extension of India. It was kind of a
peninsula of India.
So, that's how it was.
So, because there was an ice age at the
time,
uh sea levels were about 120 to 150 m
below what they are today.
Significantly lower than what the sea
levels are today. Today it's risen
significantly.
Which is why you had so much more
landmass that was available to you, but
most of it was frozen, especially in the
higher latitudes. So, this now submerged
landmass was called is is today it's
called Doggerland.
Let's Google it, shall we? So that you
get an idea of what I'm talking about.
Uh
it was called Doggerland.
Doggerland.
Yep. It was a large land area
northern Europe, now submerged beneath
the southern North Sea. So, here's what
it kind of looked like.
As you can see, what is today Britain
and Ireland was part of this extended
peninsula, which was all above the
ocean.
Uh
and you had various kinds of flora and
fauna that inhabited this region. You
also had humans, obviously.
Uh
You would
So, what kind of flora and fauna? The
flora and fauna of Europe. You would
have mammoths, you would have wolves,
you would have uh
various bovine animals, aurochs.
What sort of humans did we have there?
Uh
about 10,000 years ago you would have
Homo sapiens. You go back uh When did
this landmass
form? I mean, it was it was always
there, but when did it when did it come
above uh the sea level? Maybe 40,000
years before today, roughly.
Maybe maybe before that. Uh
it's So, at some point in time you would
have had Neanderthals who lived there.
But when this went under the sea, at
that time you would have Homo sapiens.
Uh ancient Homo sapiens would have lived
there. So, it it was it was
significantly extensive uh area of land.
What was life there like? It was very
prehistoric life.
It was a hunter-gatherer life.
There was no agriculture, there was no
nothing that we would today recognize as
civilization. It was people living in
small groups, small bands, hunting,
gathering, living hand to mouth, wearing
skins, living in caves,
uh eating essentially
flesh of animals and whatever roots and
fruits and whatever else they could
forage.
That sort of thing. That was
the kind of life that humans lived
in Doggerland at that time. And you do
find artifacts from time to time that
wash up on the beaches.
And uh yeah, so that's how it was.
Yeah, so
even if you look at uh
you know,
ancient India
from about 10,000 years ago, you'll find
that there are so many
If you if you go to the Gulf of Khambat
region,
okay? Gujarat.
Well,
there are at that time see in in Europe,
at that time you had people who were
living the hunter-gatherer lifestyle.
Eating, you know, hunting animals and
foraging for roots and and shoots and
whatnot.
In India, in the Gulf of Khambat, you
have a Gulf of Khambat archaeological
complex,
which is a network of ancient cities,
which lies on the on the on the ocean
bed, on the seabed.
And it lies at a depth of around, I
don't know, 50 to 100 m below the sea
level, which means that it was last
above sea level about 10,000 years
before today.
So, in ancient India, our ancestors,
they built cities
that are now submerged under the sea.
And even in southern India, if you go to
the eastern coast of southern India,
Tamil Nadu, etc., you will find that
they we are discovering ancient cities
that go that date back 10 10, 11,000
years.
Whenever there's a very low tide or
whatever, sometimes some ancient temples
emerge out of the ocean and then are
submerged again.
So, our civilization is incredibly
ancient, incredibly ancient. And uh we
were building cities at the time.
Like cities, what what do those cities
look like in the Gulf of Khambat region?
First of all, we have Dwarka. Dwarka is
it it went down, I don't know, maybe 8
or 5,000 years ago. Uh
whatever little uh carbon dating has
been possible over there, uh does seem
to indicate a date of date of about
8,000 years before today, a piece of
wood at least.
And ancient Dwarka is laid out just like
in Saraswati Sindhu era city,
metropolitan city with a grid structure
and well-planned thing. And even the
Gulf of Khambat archaeological complex
cities are planned like that, just like
the later Harappan so-called the
Harappan era cities, exactly like that.
So, well, incredible, isn't it?
So, that's uh
that's how ancient our our civilization
is.
Okay. Krishna of the Suriname,
Netherlands, says, "Which Iranian
ethnicity comes closest to the ethnicity
of Bharatvarsha?
The Elamites, the Medes, the Parthians,
or the Persians?"
First of all, is is Bharat one
ethnicity?
If you ask the foreigners, if you ask
the
If you ask geneticists etc. they will
say that you know Bharat is in multiple
ethnicities.
Two major ethnicities they will say
Dravidians and Aryans.
People like me are the the evil Aryan
invaders, descendant of ancient white
people who brought the evil
evil Hinduism and evil Sanskrit and evil
caste system with us with our
ancestors. And the original Indians are
the Dravidians. Anyway, so if you ask
foreigners, if you ask even Indian
researchers they will say that India
itself is multi-ethnic.
That's what they will say.
But genetics tell you that even in
northern India southern southern India,
if you
well, do a DNA sampling and if you do
see the test results, you'll find that
India has essentially the same genetics.
Even within north India and south India,
people who look so apparently
superficially different, the genetics
are very much the same.
So anyway, let's
consider India or Bharatvarsha to be one
ethnicity, okay?
So then the question arises, which
Iranian ethnicity comes closest? Ancient
Iranian ethnicity. Today you don't have
all these ethnicities like the Medes,
the Elamites, the Parthians, Persians.
So first of all, let's see okay,
uh what am I doing?
Give me a second. Uh let's first of all
Google this the the Persian ancient
Persian ethnicities and where they were
located on the map of Persia, okay?
Uh
ancient
Persian ethnicities.
Okay, so let's go to images and
hopefully we will find something
ethnicity map. Okay, tick here. Do it
this way. Ethnicities in Iran.
Not this. I said ancient. Wikipedia
seems to No, I think it's Google's
fault, not Wikipedia's fault. This is a
slightly
Okay, they are just giving you like very
recent stuff. Okay, so now
uh let us go go to
Medes uh Mar Hashi
uh you haven't heard the word Mar Hashi,
right?
Uh
Parthia
Elam map. Okay, now hopefully it gives
you some better thing.
Not Marathi, Mar Hashi.
See, even Google seems to have slightly
low IQ these days.
Anyway, so where we
Persis
Babylonia Media Persia. Okay, this gives
us a better idea of things. Elam is over
here. As you can see, Elam is in the uh
northern part of the Gulf
the Persian Gulf. Then you have Media
which is further north of Elam. Then you
have Persia, then you have uh so
whatever that is, Arya, Parthia, etc.
Uh Mar Hashi map. What about Mar Hashi?
Mar Hashi map.
Elam
and Mar Hashi map. Okay.
Do we have something? Yeah, Mar Hashi.
Okay, we have Mar Hashi Mar Hashi here.
We have Elam here. This is about 1500 BC
or something. Maybe 2000 BC, maybe even
before that.
Uh Meluhha is us. Meluhha is India. And
Mar Hashi and Meluhha actually once
allied in a war against uh
against the
Assyrians Akkadians, whichever it was.
Uh
So you had all these ethnicities in
Persia. Okay, first of all, Mar Hashi is
a little older than that.
Parthia
and
uh
Media
map.
Okay, Persia Persis Media. Okay.
So we have Parthia Bactria which is
Gandhara and west of Gandhara. Bactria
is Gandhara. West of Gandhara is
Parthia.
Persia is is west of Balochistan, okay?
And Media is northwest Persia of today,
northwest Iran of today.
So now the question, okay, after seeing
the map and getting some context, okay,
now that we have it,
uh let us discuss which ethnicity comes
closest. So if you
if you believe if you assume that
Bharatvarsha is divided into into two
ethnicities, Aryans and Dravidians,
in that case there is this hypothesis
which has no proof.
Okay, there is something called the
Elamite Dravidian Elamo-Dravidian
hypothesis.
Which is that the people of Elam
Mhm? West of Balochistan
ancient Elam they were somehow related
to the so-called Dravidian people of
India, apparently. This is a hypothesis
which has zero proof, but it's a very
famous and
influential hypothesis for some reason
without any evidence whatsoever.
So the evidence is that apparently the
people of southern Iran look quite
dark-skinned compared to people from
let's say other parts of Iran
compared to people from Gujarat
Rajasthan or or Punjab or whatever, the
people of the Balochistan and that
region they look quite dark-skinned.
Similar to the the people of southern
India. So maybe there is some kind of
connection.
Huh?
So that has given rise to the
Elamo-Dravidian hypothesis. So according
to this hypothesis
the Elamite
uh ethnicity is very close to the
so-called Dravidian ethnicity in India.
And the Parthians and the Medes and the
Persians are closer to the Indian Aryans
which is the uh people from northern and
western India.
That's what it says.
That's what the hypothesis says. Is
there any proof
that bolsters this hypothesis? None
whatsoever. That's how it works these
days.
That's how it works. You just create a
consensus of scholars and then without
proof you can put you can start
treating
uh hypothesis as as gospel truth.
So overall, if you were to ask me,
the
the Parthians, the Persians, the Medes
even if you assume that the Elamites are
different,
at least these three ethnicities they
are very similar to the other Indian
Aryan ethnicities, Indo-Aryan
ethnicities,
which is the different linguistic groups
which is which are the same people
essentially.
So that's how it is, it's complicated. I
would say India Persia very similar
historically.
In the past 1500 years things have
changed in Persia and the ethnicities
have changed because the Turks brought
in lots of foreign
uh individuals into Persia and settled
them in Persia. People from the Caucasus
region, people from Turkic-speaking
parts of Central Asia were settled in
Persia. And that changed the ethnic
makeup of Persia. Today if you look at
Persia only half of the people of Persia
are actual Persians and even those
Persians aren't pure Persians anymore.
Very few pure Persians would remain. And
the pure Persians would would have
looked 1500 years ago
like us.
At least the people of northern and
western India.
And things have changed now. So yeah.
Okay.
Uh
Hrithik Pawar says, "Why did two great
kings who ruled almost the same extent
of the empire of empire, Chandragupta
Maurya and Samudragupta, adopt very
different systems of administration?"
Chandragupta
Maurya
had a highly centralized administration
while Samudragupta relied on vassals and
a more decentralized structure. What
were the reasons for this difference?
So the two empires are roughly
800 600
So
Samudragupta, when did he rule? Sometime
in the third or fourth centuries AD,
right?
Around the fourth century AD.
Chandragupta Maurya would have ruled
roughly 800 years before him.
800 years makes a huge difference. Huge
difference. Let's understand the
context. Chandragupta Maurya was the
founder
of the Maurya Empire, correct?
And he did this by overthrowing the
Nanda Empire
through warfare.
And with the help of his mentor, the the
great Vishnugupta Chanakya. So
when Chandragupta Maurya overthrew
the Nanda Empire, he took over the
administration of what used to be the
realm of the
Nanda Empire, that particular part of
Bharatvarsha.
Chandragupta Maurya
during his lifetime did not rule the
entirety of Bharatvarsha. He did not. He
ruled a subset of Bharatvarsha.
And the Nanda Empire had ensured that it
was a centralized administration with no
vassals.
So Chandragupta Maurya took over
and he essentially uh
strengthened strengthened that structure
and made it a completely centralized
structure. At that time there were no
challengers
in that particular region to his rule.
So there was no need to placate some of
the rulers and turn them into vassals.
There was no one to challenge him. So he
became the sole ruler and eventually his
grandson Ashoka extended the rule to the
entirety of the subcontinent including
Gandhara and so on. And once again his
rule was unchallenged because there was
no one to challenge him. There were no
rulers.
Uh I mean, see, when the Greeks when the
Seleucids handed over Gandhara back to
India to
uh to the Maurya Empire,
they handed it over without any
governors or any vassals of theirs. So
it came immediately under central
central administration from Pataliputra.
And similarly other parts of India. For
example, after after the Kalinga war,
Kalinga came under direct administration
because it defeated Kalinga. There was
no one to stand now against him. So
because of the way things
things went before because of the way uh
historical events happened, it so
happened that the Mauryan Empire was
completely centrally ruled. Now when it
comes to Samudragupta,
he expanded his rule to the whole of the
subcontinent through warfare.
Samudragupta when made this very famous
uh
conquest of southern India. It was a
dual
conquest.
Two two uh you know, two vectors of
conquest. One was overland, the other
was naval.
So, at the same time that he was um you
know, conquering southern India on land,
he also had a naval conquest going on in
parallel.
And at that time in southern India, you
had many kingdoms and dynasties that
were there for a significant period of
time.
And if you were to kill those kings
and take over rule, start ruling
centrally, that would make the people
very unhappy. And if people are unhappy,
they are really hard to rule. Correct?
Which is why
uh Samudragupta adopted the policy
of just turning those kings into
vassals. So, they will continue ruling,
but they will rule in my name.
They will rule in my name. They will no
longer be maharajahs or whatever. They
will simply be governors who will rule
in my name, and they will pay me tribute
every year as per my requirements. I
will tell them how much tribute to pay
me, and they will pay me that tribute
every every year, and they will honor
me.
So, the
that's how it went in the Gupta period.
And that's why there you have these
significant differences.
So, it was pragmatic. It was practical.
Chandragupta was a practical ruler. He
knew that he could kill off all these
kings and then rule by force, but it
would make the people unhappy, and you
don't want an unhappy population.
You don't want that. You want the least
amount of friction. You want to achieve
the objective of unifying the
subcontinent. There are multiple ways of
doing it. So, depending on the times, on
the situation, on the circumstances, you
can adopt different different methods,
whatever is the best for today's time.
So, during Chandragupta's time, during
Samudragupta's time, it made sense to
just let those kings continue ruling, no
longer as kings, but as vassals, as
governors. It that was the best possible
uh
option, and that's why he adopted that.
Shubh says, "How was ancient India at
the forefront of science and technology
along with great cul- culture emphasis?
This destroys the communist narrative
that culture and science can't flow
together."
I I don't know what the communists like
to say, but you can't have
scientific advancement
without the right kind of culture.
You see?
A culture that allows questioning.
A culture that allows skepticism.
A culture that allows you to question
uh ideas
that have been
you know, regarded almost sacred.
If you don't have that kind of culture,
science will never progress. You will
never have scientific advancement.
So, India was that kind of a culture
where you could question openly.
Obviously, you had you you had to do it
in a proper way through the scientific
method and so on, but you were allowed
to question everything.
We had all these different philosophical
schools of thought, which were the
precursors of of scientific schools of
thought, in which you had different
models of the universe. Some of these
were purely materialistic like the
Charvaka school of thought, in which
there is no atma, there is no god,
there's nothing. The only thing that
exists is what you see and touch and
feel. Purely materialistic, that's one
way of looking at the world. You had
other ways of looking at the world as
well. You had the
yoga and Sankhya and Mimamsa and Buddha
and Jain and Vedanta and so on.
All different models. All of these
represent a different model of the
universe.
And these were often wildly
contradictory to each other. And they
they were all part of our culture. So,
everything all these different uh you
know, schools of thought and and and
schools of inquiry were were perfectly
embraced and welcomed in our culture.
That's why
you had so much scientific advancement
and development. Secondly, you had a
great education system. It was entirely
subsidia- subsidized by the state, by
whoever was your king or emperor. It
would be entirely subsidized by that by
them
by the king and the emperor or the queen
or whoever it was, which is why you
know, and these we had a great
multi-tier education system, which also
once again
ensured that science and technology were
develo- developed as much as they could,
which is why even 3 4 5,000 years ago,
5,000 years ago,
during the so-called mature Harappan
phase,
you had a fully urbanized civilization
with incredible scientific advancements.
You had
you know, harbors at at
what Lothal and Dholavira Dholavira that
are
that compare
that are comparable to the dockyard at
Visakhapatnam that can
accommodate aircraft carriers. That's
how massive these dockyards were 5,000
years ago. You had drainage systems that
still work. You had flush toilets. You
had works of hydro engineering, advanced
hydro engineering. You had
standardization of weights and measures.
Why was it like this? Because our
culture was a culture of excellence. It
was a culture of advancement. There was
a huge emphasis on science and
technology.
And also on the spiritual aspects of
life, which which is why we had so much
uh so much art,
such great temples. All of this went
hand in hand in hand.
So,
today the narrative is that if you
uh you know, if you want scientific
advancement, you have to kill culture,
you have to kill religion.
It's like you know, having a body with
just one one hand and one leg. That's
what it does.
So, India understood the the the concept
of harmony and balance,
and all aspects
of life are important. The religious and
spiritual aspect is important. The
cultural aspect is important. Science
and technology is super important,
without which you will never have great
great good living standards and so on.
So, that's what we understood, and
that's what has been destroyed. And
today, the narrative is that you have to
be rational. You have to be a
rationalistic person, and only uh you
know, you have to disregard all
religion, you have to stamp out
religion, which is the opium of the
masses and all the nonsense.
So, this is nothing but an attempt to
destroy India's culture. It has nothing
to do with science and technology, but
they are using the the garb of
scientific thinking and scientific
temper, that that idiotic term,
to uh try and disrupt our culture.
Feminist Slayer says, "Why was the USSR
considered a superpower? What were its
capabilities in projecting power and
controlling the global economy?"
Well, we had two superpowers in the 20th
century, 20th century.
And neither of these two superpowers
controlled the global economy. They
controlled
uh portions of the global economy.
Between them, they controlled
essentially the entire global economy,
between the two of them. But neither of
them controlled the entire global
economy. Now, the question is why is why
was or why is the USSR considered to be
a superpower? Why not just a great
power? Why why a superpower?
What were its capabilities overall? It's
not only about power power projection,
it's not only about economy, it's about
everything. It's about the whole
spectrum of capabilities that we have to
look at. So,
um first of all, uh the USSR in the 20th
century had the world's largest standing
army.
Hm?
More than 5 million soldiers could be
deployed on demand.
Maybe 5 and 1/2 million soldiers could
be deployed on demand. At at the peak of
its powers I'm talking about. You had
phases of of time when you had maybe
fewer soldiers, but at the peak of its
power, it had about 5 to 5 and 1/2
million soldiers who could be deployed
impressed into service on demand. That's
massive.
That's just the the regular forces. You
had reserves.
The USSR had reserve forces, about 30 35
million reserves, manpower.
Enormous, massive military power. That's
the conventional military power. They
had a huge industrial base, massive
industrial base, high technology,
which produced all the weapons the USSR
needed. So, they had massive
conventional capabilities. The
industrial base ensured that whatever
weaponry was required was available, as
much as you wanted.
That's why US the USSR was frightening
was frightening to to its adversaries.
That's just the conventional
capabilities.
The USSR had massive
uh stockpiles of nuclear weapons.
And that's why it essentially
counterbalanced the US.
And because of that, you had the concept
of mutually assured destruction. Both
the nations could entirely annihilate
each other.
So, once again, it it perfectly
counterbalanced the United States.
Economically, it was the world's largest
uh second largest economy after the US
until the 1980s, when Japan surpassed
the USSR and set off alarm bells in the
US, which is what the US
did some tweaks, which is which ended up
destroying Japan's economy. And today,
Japan is a
uh almost like a middle-income nation,
no longer a high-income nation. The
Americans ensured that happened. So, now
back to the USSR.
It was the world's second largest
economy for the
for the most part of the second half of
the 20th century.
Um it was the USSR was an autarky. Every
raw material, every resource you could
imagine, was available in its own
territory. It did not depend on anybody
for imports.
Everything. Minerals, uh
fertilizers, chemicals,
uh iron ore,
agricultural products, whatever they
needed was available on their own
territory. No need for imports, oil,
gas, whatever.
Then when it comes to naval
capabilities, they had a massive navy.
They had uh
submarines, you know, some of the best
submarines in the world, nuclear
submarines that could launch ballistic
missiles and various kinds of missiles.
And the USSR's navy patrolled every
ocean in the world.
Okay?
It patrolled every ocean. So, global
power projection capabilities through
the navy.
And through the ballistic missiles, the
ICBMs that they had.
When it comes to
power projections power projections once
again, they had
military bases in various parts of the
world. They had military bases in Africa
in Ethiopia
in
Sudan Sudan most likely in Egypt for a
while until the 1950s they had bases in
Egypt. They had bases in Syria Tartus
Latakia.
One of those is still there. They had
bases in Libya they had
bases in Cuba in Venezuela.
Until the 1950s they had bases they had
military bases in China as well.
Vietnam as well because of the
ideological
coherence and so on. So they they had
significant power project I'm sure I've
missed some out maybe somewhere in
Africa some more but you you get the
point.
They had power projection capabilities
everywhere. They also had bases in
Eastern Europe through the Warsaw Pact.
And they had many countries that were
ideologically aligned with them and they
had these
treaties like the Warsaw Pact which
brought the nations together under the
leadership of the USSR. You had other
nations like Vietnam and etc also which
were completely ideologically aligned
with them. So all these things taken
together is what made the USSR a
superpower right?
Amisha Mishra says difference between
Creole Creole populations in mixed race
once New Spain.
New Spain.
So when you talk about New Spain you
don't really think about Creole
populations there.
New Spain is uh
is essentially
Mexico and the territories north of
Mexico today. So in the in the 1500s
after Christopher Columbus discovered
what he thought was India but it ended
up being the so-called New World. After
that the Spaniards were very very quick
in colonizing these parts of the world.
Um
and
you know
they had a territory in Mexico from
there they expanded northwards
into much of what is currently the US
California Arizona Colorado
Tejas all of that. You had various
expeditions which which took place
initially in the first half of the
1500s. You had the Narvaez expedition
Panfilo de Narvaez Alvar Nunez Cabeza de
Vaca Estevanico all these fantastic
individuals. Panfilo de Narvaez well his
story ends very quickly but whatever. So
that was in the 1520s to 1530s. The
Narvaez expedition. Then you had the
Coronado expedition Francisco Vasquez de
Coronado.
With with him there were wonderful
people like Fray Marcos de Niza and they
went to Cibola and Quivira and so on.
That was in the 1540s.
And through these expeditions and there
were many more okay
and these are not nice things actually
for the natives. So through these
expeditions and so on
they slowly made their way into what is
now the United States and they colonized
all this all these parts of the what is
today the US. And all of this was
eventually called New Spain mainly New
Spain means Mexico Mexico.
Now
the populations in New Spain
so what happened is that when when they
did these expeditions and when they
conquered for example the
the Aztec Empire
in what is what is now Mexico Mexico
City Tenochtitlan then there was further
conquest
of the of the Inca Empire
in the
west coast of northwestern coast of
South America and so on Peru etc.
Then what happened is that there was
there was this tremendous outbreaks of
epidemics which killed a significant
amount of the population. There were
massacres and genocide also but done by
the Spaniards and the enslavement of the
natives and the imposition of Spanish
religion which is Christianity on the
natives by force of course by destroying
the native temples and building churches
on top of them for example Mexico City
and so on.
And eventually the
the subjugated peoples intermingled with
the with the conquerors and gave rise to
a new race of people.
Even even if you go to Mexico today this
small minority which is still pure white
which
which looks white
and most people are still brown
and most of them have have mixed and
these people aren't called Creole. They
are called what are they called?
They just called Mexicans I suppose.
So what is Creole then is the question.
So the Creole populations don't really
have much to do
with New Sp- what was called New Spain.
That term Creole is not used for these
mixed race populations.
There was a term called Mestizo that was
used for a while and so on. But when it
comes to the word Creole it's usually
generally used for native people who
intermingled with the French colonizers
not the Spanish colonizers.
It's the same thing.
It's the same thing mixed race people
with mixed languages. But it's only used
as far as I am aware for natives who
intermingled with French colonizers. For
example New Orleans Nouvelle Orleans
which is um
Louisiana
yeah it's it's the mouth of the
Mississippi River.
So if you go if you go to New Orleans
there's still a French Quarter which was
rebuilt actually it's not the original
French Quarter but the people who live
there they they
you know the the mixed race people who
were combination of French colonizers
and
black slaves and whatnot they were
called Creole people and their languages
was kind of a mixture of French and
African words.
And another place where you have Creole
is in Mauritius Ile Maurice.
So the the Creole they speak there it
sounds French the accent is French the
grammar is French the structure overall
is French lots of French vocabulary but
you also have Indian words
Hindi Tamil words and you also have
some African words sprinkled into the
mix. So that also is called Creole
Mauricien.
Mauritius Creole.
Um the people of Mauritius are fantastic
amazing people outstanding people.
If you hear them if you listen to them
speak they'll sound very French it's
like you it's a French person speaking.
But you look at them they look entirely
Indian.
And the way they eat they're more Indian
than me they'll sit on the floor and eat
rice with their fingers. I can't do
that. Okay.
So yeah so
that's what I that's how
that's how I understand Creole. Creole
is French origin.
It's it's native people. So it's not
just the language that is called Creole
language but maybe even the people are
called Creole people.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay next.
Yajnavalkya says who are the Samaritans?
Is Samaritanism considered a sect of
Judaism or an entirely different
religion? Did Christians treat
Samaritans the same as other pagans and
thus almost wipe Samaritans out
unlike the more favorable treatment
given to Jews? Very interesting
questions question
questions. Who are these Samaritans? How
many Abrahamic religions actually exist?
We all are reasonably familiar with the
Abrahamic religions here in India. We
have been exposed to at least a couple
of those not a very good exposure but
whatever.
Not the most pleasant exposure
historically.
Today's context is different. I'm
talking about historically.
So we are aware of three Abrahamic
religions.
Christianity
Islam and Judaism and as far as we know
Judaism is the original Abrahamic
religion. A prophet Ibrahim or Abraham
was
a Jewish prophet wasn't he?
The Muslims also consider him to be a
prophet of Islam they also consider
Jesus to be a prophet of Islam and so
on.
So yeah okay.
But there's another Abrahamic religion
which is Samaritanism.
So what what is all this about right? So
first of all there was there is a place
called Samaria.
And the ancient people who lived in
Sama- in Samaria are called were called
Samaritans and their descendants are
also called Samaritans today. So now
first of all let's go and Google this.
Samaria what is Samaria?
Samaria. Oh look at this ancient place
with ruins.
So it's a Hebrew name Shomron etc.
It's it's a central region in Israel. So
if you go to the map okay.
If you go to map
you will see that the central part of
Israel between the West Bank
and to some extent the sea
from the river to the sea is is is
Samaria.
Um
So this region essentially
pretty large region that's Samaria and
there is a there is a specific place in
in the center somewhere
which is also called Samaria.
Okay I'm I'm not sure I'll be able to
locate it over here.
But it's it's the central region of
Israel and it has been described
variously as as something that begins
with the from the West Bank of the River
Jordan
to a certain part of Israel and some
some historians have said it goes all
the way to the sea.
So that's the that is what Samaria is.
Historically that was the region of
Samaria today no I I don't think anyone
calls Samaria today.
And the people who lived there
were called the Samaritan people.
Now what did they believe in? What was
their belief system? It was very similar
to Judaism but slightly different.
They believed in the God Yahweh
that the Jews believe in Yahweh.
They also regard the Torah
as their holy book.
But beyond that there are some
differences which even I don't know
really what exactly the differences are.
I haven't studied this in detail, but
the point is that there are differences.
There are other books in
religious beliefs that differ from
Judaism.
So a significant part of their belief
system is identical to Judaism, the
belief in the God Yahweh, and the the
the the fact that they regard the Torah
as the central holy book. But beyond
that there are divergences that details
you can look up if you're interested.
There are divergences, which is why most
scholars regard Samaritanism as a
separate Abrahamic religion distinct
from Judaism.
Despite them
sharing the same God and the in the
Torah as well. Still there are some
differences. Just like people say that
Buddhism, Hinduism are different and
Hinduism and other Sikhism, Jainism
today everything is different.
Similarly, even Samaritanism and
Judaism are different apparently.
Now um
Samaritanism There is something called
the good Samaritan, right?
Everyone uses this term good Samaritan
for someone who does something
out of the generous generosity of their
heart. So I think it was a parable that
was allegedly um
said by Shri Jesus
uh Mr. Jesus, the good the parable of
the good Samaritan. So even during Shri
Jesus's time, which is 0 1 AD or
whatever it was, at that time the
Samaritans
uh in the first
first 30 40 years of the first century
AD
even at that time the Samaritans were
regarded as a separate religion from the
Jews, and they were not entirely
friendly with each other. They were kind
of rivals or hostile to each other,
Samaritans and Jews. And Shri Jesus gave
this parable that you know some Jewish
guy was injured and priests and other
people walked by him just not caring,
but a Samaritan came and helped him and
gave him water and
Okay. Okay, we're back. So
So apparently that's what happened. Um
And so that that person is called the
good Samaritan. So a Samaritan who he
who who was hostile to the Jewish people
still uh
was nice to a Jew and took care of the
person and took him to a hospital or inn
or something and ensured the person
survived. So that's the good Samaritan
tale or parable.
Uh now
So the Jews in the fifth or sixth
whichever century BC
uh they were forced into exile into the
Babylonian exile, the rivers of Babylon
that song.
And then after a few years after a few
decades they were allowed back into
Judea into what is presently Israel.
Uh and then
they came under you know Judaism it it
came the Jews dispersed the diaspora and
all and they
various points in time they came under
Christian rule.
And also under Muslim rule as we know.
And the Christians and the Muslims they
mainly regarded the Jews as people of
the book, which is why the Jews were
given a special protection and special
privileges.
But the Samaritans were somehow not
considered people of the book and they
were treated more harshly.
During the Byzantine empire they were
treated harshly. During the Muslim rule
they were treated harshly. There used to
be massacres of the Samaritans. There
used to be forcible conversions of the
Samaritans, which is why there you have
very few Samaritans who survived today.
Uh they were not the Samaritans were not
treated as badly as the pagans. What is
what does paganism mean from a Abrahamic
perspective? Today even Indians who say
that we are pagans.
Why do you have to define yourself from
someone else's worldview? Why this
inferiority complex? We are pagans. We
are us. Anyway, from an Abrahamic
perspective paganism means polytheism,
very evil, the worst sin you can
imagine.
The polytheists shall burn in all
eternity for all eternity in hellfire
apparently. That's the fate that awaits
us. Unless unless we embrace a superior
religion or something. Whatever. So
So the
Samaritans were not treated as badly as
the as the polytheists, as the pagans.
So the best treatment was given to the
Jews.
The second best or second first
treatment was given to the Samaritans
and the worst treatment was given to
polytheists.
That's how the cookie crumbled. That's
how the dice rolled. Next.
Geopolitical Dubey says it is said that
sage Shalihotra was the first veterinary
veterinarian who lived during Ashoka's
rule.
Can you shed some light on this?
Okay, so Geopolitical Dubey has been
asking this question for a very long
time, so that I thought I'll take this
up today.
Look, there's very little that's known
about sage Shalihotra.
Shalihotra is said to have lived
sometime during the Mauryan era, maybe
the third century BC or something, which
kind of possibly coincides with Ashoka's
rule.
So Shalihotra
was a veterinary veterinarian. He
compiled a treatise called the
Shalihotra Samhita I think.
In which
he describes all kinds of ailments and
and diseases and problems that can
afflict uh
mainly two species of
two families of animals, which is the
cattles, cows, buffaloes, etc. mainly
cows obviously,
and the horses, the equine animals, the
horses. Because these are the two most
important animals and I'm sure also also
the the the the the uh
elephant. Elephant, yes. Elephant.
So
that's what he did and he was
he was very knowledgeable about this. He
knew exactly all the diseases, all the
troubles that could afflict these
animals and he knew how to
and he prescribed various
solutions, surgical, non-surgical, etc.
solutions to various problems. So it's a
pretty thick thesis in which he has
given a tremendous amount of knowledge
and obviously he did not
invent all of these treatments and so on
ab initio from scratch. He also learned
this from somewhere. It's an old
tradition that was going on, but he's
the first person who compiled all this
knowledge into one
book as far as we know. Maybe there were
others, but all that has been lost.
So uh
that's the deal. I mean even during the
Mahabharata era you it is said that the
Nakula and Sahadeva were were well
versed in the treatment of various
animals, the cattles and the ashwas I
believe, cattles and the horses.
Elephants was what was it? Something
like that.
Uh so I would not say that Shalihotra
was the first veterinarian. I mean I
would say that he is the first known
veterinarian.
Uh and he probably lived in the like
like I said around the third century BC.
Well, if you want to talk about people
who knew a lot about horses, I can talk
tell you about Kikkuli.
Kikkuli was a horse master, horse
trainer whose mother tongue was
Sanskrit, but who lived in what is now
Anatolia and Syria. He was he belonged
to the Mitanni empire.
And he wrote a horse breeding manual in
the Hurrian language, but some terms he
had to use Sanskrit terms because those
terms did not exist, technical terms did
not exist in the Hurrian language. So he
had to use his mother tongue, Sanskrit.
So he also knew a lot about horse
training. He knew how to take a regular
horse and transform that horse over a
period of two three months into a
properly trained war horse. And
obviously there will be treatment and
whatnot involved in that. So this
knowledge was there with us for a very
long time. The Mitanni rulers they are
known to have
been ruling the Mitanni kingdom empire
around 1300 1200 AD BC.
That's at least about a thousand years
before Shalihotra.
And they would have reached that part of
the world a few centuries before that.
So around 2000 BC they would have had a
high quality understanding of how to
deal with horses.
Treatment, training, everything. So this
knowledge has been around for a very
long time, but Shalihotra is the first
person that we know of who compiled all
of this knowledge into a single volume
actual volume. I'm sure this knowledge
was around for a very long time,
thousands of years before Shalihotra
himself.
But yeah, he's the first person that we
know of, the original veterinarian who
wrote a treatise, a proper treatise in
which everything, all the information,
all the knowledge was compiled about
horses and
and and and and cattle and possibly also
elephants.
And this Shalihotra Samhita was
translated into all kinds of languages,
into Arabic, into Persian, into Tibetan,
into Chinese and whatnot. Everyone took
the knowledge.
And now it is world knowledge.
Okay.
Nirvana Shanks says, "Should King Sudas
of the Bharatas clan, after whom the
subcontinent is traditionally named,
after the Bharatas clan, should he
Sudas, King Sudas, be called the father
of Bharat?
Or should Chandragupta Maurya, the who
first politically united the
subcontinent, hold that title?"
Uh okay. Does
does Bharat need a father?
So whoever is the gentleman who is
considered to be the father of the
nation
that person certainly I would not agree
is the father of the nation.
The father is someone who creates,
right?
The father is somebody who creates
something new.
Our fathers created us, right?
So did the gentleman who is considered
to be the father of the nation create
Bharat really?
So then the question is should somebody
be given this title?
And should does somebody actually
deserve it?
So, King Sudas
did he create Bharatvarsha?
To some extent he did.
To some extent.
He
for the first time I would say united
He He essentially was
the Genghis Khan of his time.
He defeated everybody and brought
everybody in the sub at least large part
of the subcontinent together under a
single dominion.
Kind of.
Genghis Khan was also like that. I mean
he was fighting every He was up against
everyone alone.
And one by one he defeated everybody.
One by one.
Uh Sudas, he did not defeat everybody
one by one. He defeated them all in one
shot.
Uh so, there are some similarities
between Sudas and Genghis Khan.
But we don't know that much about Sudas.
But what Sudas did is that after
defeating all the adversaries and
expelling them out of India
he then chose to be magnanimous
and
all-embracing.
So,
he said that look, we have a certain set
of gods, the Arya gods.
Indra and Indra was the
you know the the
the
primary god. The most powerful god of
that time. For our ancestors.
Then you had various other gods, you
know, Mitra, Varuna, all that. The Vedic
pantheon of gods.
And the Bharat clan they had this
ritual, the Yagna ritual, in which
various offerings would be done to the
gods through the medium of Agni who was
the messenger of the gods and he Agni is
a major god himself.
So, Bharat said that okay, I have now
conquered this entire region.
And he told the people of the region
that your gods are welcome
to
to the Yagna.
So, it's we will not just pray to our
gods. Your gods are also welcome and you
can all give your offerings and we will
all be one people now.
So, whatever cultural differences we may
have, let's combine all of that and make
it a single culture, a unified culture.
And that is what gave rise to Bharatiya
culture.
So, to very large extent I would say
Sudas does deserve
at least way more deserving than whoever
it is, I'm not sure who it is, but
whoever is considered to be the father
of the nation today. Sudas, sure.
Was there someone before Sudas? I'm sure
there was, but yeah, let's let's talk
about Sudas here. Way more deserving,
Sudas. Chandragupta Maurya
Chandragupta Maurya did not politically
unite the subcontinent. He He
He founded the Mauryan dynasty. Which
eventually unified the subcontinent
through Chandragupta's grandson Ashoka
Maurya.
Chandragupta Maurya planted the seeds
and he did conquer and unite a
significant part of the subcontinent.
But he did not conquer the whole of the
subcontinent. Less than half.
His grandson finished the job. He
unified Bharatvarsha properly.
Um
So, more than Chandragupta I would give
it to Ashoka.
More than him I would give it to Ashoka.
Okay.
Amisha Mishra says, "The Mongols nearly
conquered half the world. Why isn't
Mongolia a great nation today?"
"India was the most advanced
civilization in the world. Why are we so
mediocre and third world today?"
Same.
Same question can be asked. The same
question can be asked.
Right?
Uh
Because everything rises and falls. If
you
if you lower your standards, you're
going to decline and you're going to
lose your greatness.
So, Mongolia did conquer half the world.
Half Actually it conquered I would say,
if I think about it
slightly more than half the known world.
Probably
a good amount more than half the known
world. So, at the time
we weren't aware of Australia, we
weren't aware of Antarctica, we weren't
aware of North and South America. We
only knew Eurasia and Africa.
And he conquered more than half of
Eurasia. Genghis Genghis and his
descendants the
cumulatively conquered more than half of
Eurasia.
And they did this because they were
superior.
They had superior strategies, superior
tactics, they were superior
organization, superior administration,
superior uh
uh communications and superior logistics
and everything else.
Right? That's why they were able to
conquer.
Uh superior discipline, superior
standards, everything. That's why they
were able to conquer half the world,
more than half the world.
Then
standards declined.
The empire fragmented. There was
infighting.
The sons and grandsons of Genghis Khan,
they went and con you know, they were
ruling in far
far far apart territories and they
eventually started
drifting apart.
And they no longer recognized or or
regarded their blood ties
more important than their their personal
ambitions.
And that's why there were conflicts.
Some of them became Islamized and
Turkicized.
And what was left behind in Mongolia
eventually the
the root the the the heart of the of the
empire was Mongolia itself and over
there you know, political power no
longer
was that powerful. Because of decline.
So, there was a decline in standards and
everything else and that's why
today Mongolia is well, what it is
today.
Uh it is not regarded
as a great power or even a power that
matters in any consequential way today,
unfortunately.
Right?
The same
applies to all fallen civilizations
or empires.
Because of a decline in standards. You
no longer maintain the high standards
that took you to the pinnacle
of the world.
You no longer maintain the standards, so
obviously you're going to
decline.
And after you decline they'll be
conquered by others and that's what
happened to Mongolia as well.
So, Mongolia was conquered essentially
vassalized by the USSR and half of the
land was taken by the Chinese because of
these things.
So, that's uh
you know, it's a cautionary tale for
everyone. It applies to us as well. Look
at our standards today. Super mediocre.
Super low standards. Super third world
standards in India today you have.
It is what it is.
So, my point is the Mongols were great.
But today they don't go around claiming
that we were the greatest blah blah blah
blah we were number one blah blah blah.
But in India we have people who are
simply content to rest on the laurels of
your ancestors a thousand two thousand
years ago. What are you all doing today?
What are your standards today?
You know, intro introspect introspect.
Okay, Rinky Chaudhary says, "Why did
Prithviraj Chauhan let Muhammad Ghori
free and not capture him even after
defeating him in the first battle of
Tarain 1191?" Well,
first battle of Tarain 1191, it is known
that Prithviraj Chauhan defeated
Muhammad Ghori.
And Muhammad Ghori was captured.
His army, the Turkic army, was smashed
by Prithviraj Chauhan's army.
And Muhammad Ghori
well, was he captured? Or was he No, he
was not captured. He was allowed to
escape.
I mean he tried to escape and the
pursuit wasn't that serious. So, he was
allowed He essentially was able to
escape and return
uh to occupied Gandhara.
Right?
He
He wasn't captured. He was allowed to
escape. If we had pursued him seriously
like whatever happened you know we
didn't capture him, he would have been
captured. But he was allowed to to
escape all the way from Tarain all the
way to to Gandhara occupied Gandhara,
Afghanistan.
Um
So, yeah, I think it was we were not
serious. Okay, this guy is you know, we
were able to defeat him, he doesn't
matter anymore.
And let him go. Who cares? I think that
was the deal.
Um
Why did Prithviraj Chauhan do this?
Now, we don't know him personally. We
don't have any podcasts or interviews
with him, so we don't know, but we can
guess
based on culture and civilization. See,
let me give you a very strange example.
You all will find it very strange, but
let me give you this example
nonetheless.
The greatest one of the greatest novels
in French literature
is considered to be
Victor Hugo's Les Misérables.
In English you would say Les Misérables.
Let me Google it and I'll let me show
you.
It's called Les Misérables.
Okay?
Les Misérables is a It's not a novel
man, not movie.
Novel.
Okay, it's a book by It's a novel by
Victor Hugo. Greatest novel of the 19th
century and so on. It was written It was
published in 1862. It's about It's about
France. And of course there there are
movies made about the the book and so
on. So, if you go to images
So, who's the protagonist? The
protagonist is a guy whose name is Jean
Valjean. Okay? The protagonist, his name
is Jean Valjean. He is a convict. He's a
petty criminal who has been jailed for
stealing a loaf of bread.
And
he eventually goes on parole and he does
some other small crime. And then there
is the antagonist of the novel is
Inspector Javert.
Inspector Javert is a man of the law. He
believes that the law is the only thing
that keeps society
you know, working fine.
And his life's purpose is to uphold the
law and to punish all criminals.
So he's a very upright man, very serious
man, no sense of humor. His only mission
in life is to uphold the law. And he
goes after
So Inspector Javert, let me show you
what it look what it look like, okay?
Just so that you have a image in your
mind.
In the 1998 movie
Javert, Inspector Javert, extremely
serious man, no sense of humor, but not
an evil man.
He is doing the right job. He's He's
pursuing the purpose of his life. And
you have Jean Valjean.
Valjean.
Jean, that's Liam Neeson.
This gentleman, okay? Uh Valjean, okay.
So this is the protagonist and uh Javert
is the antagonist.
So Javert pursues Jean Valjean his
entire life for decades. And eventually
in the end of the of the of the novel,
you have Javert
who is trying to put down a student
insurrection.
And Jean Valjean has been discovered
again. He wants to put Jean Valjean
Jean Valjean in jail.
And Jean Valjean captures this guy in
front of the students. He says, "I'm
going to take him to the court street
corner and shoot him."
He takes him to the street corner.
Fires a shot in the air and releases the
guy. He says, "The You leave now. Once
this revolution is over, you can come in
come in imprison me. I am tired of
running my whole life. You can put me in
jail. I'll be done with it."
And then Jean Valjean and then Javert is
wondering, "What do I do with this guy?
I've been pursuing him my entire life
because he he was a criminal.
And every time he has done something
good with his life.
He became the mayor of a town until I
discovered that he's a criminal. Then he
went and
to a different place, escaped from that
place. Again, he did something good with
his life.
And here, he should have killed me, but
he let me go.
So I Jean Valjean, I mean I Javert
believe that those who break the law are
evil people.
That's why they have to be punished.
But this man, Jean Valjean, is not evil.
He's not evil.
So how can I punish him? But if I don't
punish him, I'm breaking my own
principles.
So Javert goes and kills kills himself
because he's totally conflicted.
So he was a man of principles, Javert.
Prithviraj Chauhan
was a man of principle.
He believed that you have to treat
you know, behave in a certain way in the
world. You should You should be
inflexible in your behavior.
You should go by the
the dharmic principles, what he believed
to be the dharmic principles. Which
means be fair, be magnanimous, be just.
If somebody has been defeated, you let
them go. You don't capture them. You
don't kill them and so on.
Was it right?
Obviously it was not right.
To be entirely dharmic, you have to
follow the principles of Sri Krishna and
his and and the way
he dealt with the enemies during the
Mahabharat.
So if Prithviraj Chauhan had borrowed a
leaf from the Bhagavad Gita and from Sri
Krishna's life and actions, he would
have dealt with Muhammad Ghori
differently.
But Prithviraj Chauhan believed that he
was right and his
way of behavior and and his the actions
he took were correct. You should not uh
shoot a guy with an arrow in the back.
The guy is escaping by horse.
His army has been destroyed. He's
distraught. He's heartbroken.
It is wrong to put an arrow in a man's
back when he's escaping. Let him go.
That maybe was his
idea of being dharmic. It was obviously
completely incorrect because you should
never let a snake go. The snake will
come back tomorrow and bite you much
worse.
Uh so that's what I would say.
Prithviraj Chauhan was a great man.
But sadly, he made a mistake
which ruined India
to a very large extent.
Yep. So hopefully we can learn the
lessons from
the these examples.
Yajnavalkya says, "Why did wild aurochs
get extinct in India and in the entire
world?"
What is this aurochs thing?
You something here, hey.
What is aurochs? Let me show you.
Aurochs were a breed of wild cattle, a
species of wild cattle.
Uh aurochs.
Aurochs, that's what it looked like.
This is what the aurochs looked like.
Uh as you can see, this is a comparison
with a human being, a standard average
sized human being. And the aurochs were
pretty large.
Um
Bos taurus is the wrong cattle to see
because the Bos indicus is more close to
aurochs.
Uh so we have the
aurochs once again. If you look at size,
you have this, aurochs.
Uh and the aurochs, they
they went extinct sometime in the 16th
or 17th century AD.
Which is like just like 400 years ago.
Uh they used These were wild cattle
first of all. Okay? They These were wild
cattle and they lived in grasslands and
forest lightly forested lands all across
Asia and Europe, across Eurasia,
including India.
The closest modern day
animals that are related closely related
to the aurochs are the
zebu cattle of India.
The closest living relatives are the are
the Indian zebu cattle. What does that
look like? Let me show you in case
you're not aware.
Zebu cattle.
That's what zebu cattle looks like.
That's not a great example. This is a
great example. Your standard
Indus Sarasvati Valley
cattle.
Massive beasts. So these are the most
These are the closest relatives of the
of the aurochs that you have today.
Uh zebu cattle, okay.
Now the question is what happened to
these aurochs?
So they were
found in India. They were found across
Eurasia. They were found in Europe as
well.
And it is said that in India they went
extinct 3,000 years ago or something.
3,000
4,000 years ago or something like that.
The The reason they say that is because
it's very difficult to differentiate
between the bones of zebu and the bones
of aurochs. They are very similar,
almost the same.
So maybe it's not 3,000 years ago. Maybe
it is
200 years ago. I I don't know for sure.
But officially it's around 3,000 years
ago that they went extinct in India. And
they went extinct in Europe in different
parts of Europe at different times, but
the last known herd went extinct about
3-400 years ago.
Now the question is why did they go
extinct?
So first of all, uh
Indians were the first to domesticate
the aurochs.
And after domesticating the aurochs,
they did give right rise to a new breed
of cattle, which is the zebu cattle. The
great Indus Sarasvati re Valley region
cattle with the big hump and the big
dewlap under the chin and those horns
that the the cattle that you find in the
in the Sarasvati Sindhu seals, those
cattle.
Um
So after the domestication, what
happened is that apparently um the
natural habitat of the aurochs reduced
because that was taken over by the
domesticated cattle, which were the
relatives. And there was inbreeding
between interbreeding between the
domesticated cattle and the aurochs,
which diluted the gene pool.
And human presence spread across the
world, especially the subcontinent,
which is maybe why the aurochs lost
their natural habitat and it was all
encroached by humans and human um
engineered cattle.
And maybe that's why the aurochs
disappeared eventually in the sub Indian
subcontinent. And in various parts of
Europe, once again, you had human
encroachment into uh areas that were
naturally, you know, traditionally
aurochs, you know,
the natural habitat of aurochs.
So you had
all that land taken over by humans and
there was hunting of aurochs as well. As
the aurochs populations declined,
aurochs became a prestigious hunting
animal. So only kings and royalty were
allowed to hunt aurochs. And that was a
great sport in those days. It was called
game.
And uh eventually the aurochs was hunted
out of extinction. Uh there may have
been disease also diseases also that
were introduced by by humans and so on.
So it's it's multiple factors that
combined together to
um
you know, make the aurochs extinct. But
is it really extinct? The Indian cattle
are very closely related to the aurochs.
They are nothing but domesticated
versions of the aurochs, which then
eventually gave rise to various
different breeds.
So what was the ancestral
population of the Indian cattle? It was
the aurochs.
So I would not entirely say that it's
it's entirely extinct. They still live
in Indian Indian cattle.
Uh but yeah, that that in that size and
shape and form, it's no longer
extinct today.
Right?
All right. Next question. Saloni Mishra
says, "I recently discovered your
channel." Well, welcome to the channel.
"I want to ask you question." Oh, of
course. That's what we do here.
"Why did the Indo-Aryans migrate into
the Indian subcontinent during the
decline of the Indus Valley
civilization? And what motivated this
movement towards an environmentally
degraded region?"
Fantastic question.
So since you're new and I'm sure there
are lots and lots of people who are new
to the channel and who have not seen my
my older videos about this issue.
So let's let's take this a priori from
the beginning.
So the question is why did the
Indo-Aryans
migrate into the subcontinent during so
and so time.
Why did they migrate? So, the
presupposition you're making while
asking the question is that there was a
migration
of these foreigners who came into India.
Right? Uh if you had asked me this
question 20 years ago, if somebody else
would have asked it to it this question
20 years ago, there was a there was a
they would have said, "Why did the
Indo-Aryans invade the Indian
subcontinent?" Because 20 years ago, it
was called the Aryan invasion theory.
Today, they have
reformulated the theory and
re-christened it
into the Aryan migration theory,
Indo-Aryan migration theory.
The Aryan invasion theory has now been
converted into the Indo-Aryan migration
theory. Why was it converted into the
Indo-Aryan migration theory from an
invasion theory?
The original theory was that about 1,500
years ago 1,500 BC, a bunch of white
barbarians, white-skinned barbarians
came from Central Europe and invaded
India.
Okay? Around 1,500 BC.
At that time, India was a land populated
by Dravidian people who are a different
race and ethnicity and culture.
They are dark-skinned. The Aryans were
white-skinned barbarians, evil people.
And they invaded India, they subjugated
the peaceful, highly cultured, highly
evolved, highly civilized Dravidians
and
um oppressed them
and they relegated them to the south of
India.
And then the Aryans
settled in the former lands of the
Dravidians, and then they they
introduced their evil foreign religion,
Hinduism,
their evil foreign language, Sanskrit,
and the super evil caste system into
India.
And then they sat on the banks of the
Saraswati and wrote the Rigveda.
That's the original theory, the Aryan
invasion theory. Now, the problem with
this theory is that there is no evidence
of invasion.
There is no archaeolo- there is no
evidence whatsoever, not even a scratch
of a record in the archaeological
evidence that
indicates there was any kind of invasion
any point in time in India.
Because when there's an invasion,
it leaves archaeological traces.
When there's an invasion, there are
massacres, there are battles, people
die, they're dumped into mass graves.
You will find all these things, nothing
is there. You'll find battlefields with
broken bones and broken arrows and
broken whatnot,
broken equipment. You'll find burned
cities with with layers of ash and soot
and dust and whatnot. You find nothing
like this in India.
Anywhere around 1,500 BC, nothing.
Nothing at all.
Nothing.
That's why this invasion could not work.
So, now they have modified it to say
there was a migration, a peaceful
migration
of these evil Aryans into India.
Now, the problem with this Aryan
migration theory
is that there is no evidence of
migration again.
If these inva- these migrants
came
at so and so time, around 1,500 BC, into
India, you will see evidence of a
migration in the archaeological record.
How so?
You will see a sudden cultural change.
The Dravidians maybe had a certain way
of building constructing buildings and
all. Now, suddenly, you have a new
culture that comes in, you will
immediately see in the archaeological
layers a new culture that suddenly
appears.
Because obviously, it's a different
culture.
The white European Aryans were obviously
very different from the black
Dravidians, right? According to the
theory. So, you should see a significant
sudden change in the archaeological
record culturally cult- cultural
cultural artifacts. The Dravidians maybe
worshiped a certain certain set of
Dravidian gods, suddenly, you have the
appearance of new gods in the archaeolo-
archaeological record. Do you see that?
Do you see that?
You see nothing.
You see no discontinuity in the
archaeolo- archaeological record.
Right?
Nothing. My question is, where's the
evidence? Now, some people,
the Great Gatsby, for example, will say,
"But we have genetic evidence.
I have Aryan genes.
I have Aryan genes in my body.
I have a large number of Aryan genes,
R1A1A gene I have.
I did my genetic test.
I have the R1A1A gene in my body. It is
Aryan gene. So, Aryan invasion happened
or migration happened."
Are re baba,
first of all,
what is R1A1A?
Is it a gene?
It is not a gene.
It's a haplogroup.
What is a haplogroup?
What is it?
A haplogroup is a lineage.
In Sanskrit, we call it vansh.
A haplogroup
is a group of people who are alive today
on the surface of this planet who all
share a specific genetic mutation that
happened sometime in the past.
So, the R1A1A haplogroup
haplogroup is a set of people, males,
who are alive today on the planet, who
all share the same genetic mutation that
originally happened about 15-20,000
years ago in one single person who was
also a male.
How do I know it's males?
Because it's a Y chromosomal haplogroup.
Y chromosomes are passed on from father
to son, not from father to daughter.
Because daughters don't have Y
chromosomes, they only have XX, right?
We know that. Males are XY.
So, R1A1A,
which is also called called RM17 today,
it's a Y chromosomal haplogroup. The
original initial
um
mutation happened about 15-20,000 years
ago.
And we can kind of date how long how old
it is based on various factors, we will
not go into that.
So, today, R1A1A,
how large is this haplogroup? How many
individuals?
More than a billion.
It's the world's largest extended
family.
And
who are these people?
These are mostly the speakers of the
Indo-European languages.
There are two parts of the world where
you have huge concentrations
of R1A1A
people.
One is in India,
one is in Eastern Europe.
Yeah?
Yeah. It is what it is.
So, there is clearly some kind of
genetic connection.
But now,
tell me something, how do you know this
is the Aryan
haplogroup? How do you know it's a Aryan
family?
It seems to be kind of prevalent where
you have speakers of Indo-European
languages.
You go to
southern India,
you have as much R1A1A as as in northern
India. You go to some so-called tribal
groups who are allegedly called Adivasi
groups, Irula, etc., they have way more
R1A1A
as a percentage of the population than
most many parts of northern India.
How do you explain that?
Go to Manipur.
They don't speak a Indo-Aryan language,
right? They speak a Tibeto-Burman
Burmese language, Tibeto-Burman
language. They have significant R1A1A.
How do you explain that?
So, how do you make the claim that R1A1A
is an Aryan gene or a haplogroup? What
is the evidence?
Evidence is zero.
Whatever evidence you have,
yeah, it's it's it's it's a
it's
circumstantial evidence. It's not
evidence that will stand in a court of
law.
It is not evidence that measured up
measures up to to the scientific method.
Right?
So, once again, and my question is, if
you have a certain
genetic makeup in your body,
how does it indicate that it it is Aryan
or Dravidian or whatever?
So, the question arises, where did R1A1A
originate? This first person
in whom this genetic mutation happened,
perhaps it's India, perhaps it's Central
Asia, perhaps it's Europe, wherever,
okay?
It doesn't matter.
But whoever the first person was,
do we know what his language was? Do we
know what his religion and culture was?
Do we know that?
We don't know that.
Go to Turkey today.
If you do that
DNA tests of Turkish people, the results
are extremely inconvenient and extremely
embarrassing because they it's more than
90% 95% Greek and Armenian.
Right?
But they speak the Turkish language and
they practice the Islamic religion.
So, despite having Greek DNA, they have
a totally different culture, language,
and religion.
So, what is the connection between DNA
and language, culture, religion? Zero.
I can give you so many examples. So,
this entire genetic angle
is misleading. It is deliberately
introduced to mislead most people.
And the people who can't think deeply or
incapable of the critical thinking
because of what the education system has
done to you,
you will be the victims of this.
You have to think deeply
and thoroughly and consider all the
scenarios to understand the how they are
misleading you.
My point is, there is a zero zero zero
evidence of any Aryan invasion or
migration into India. Zero.
Show me one piece of hard evidence that
can stand up to scrutiny in a court of
law or
for the scientific method. Show me.
You'll find none.
But
they will appeal to authority. So many
eminent scientists agree, which is why
it must be true. All the books they
write about this, which is why it must
be true. Romila Thapar is a proponent of
this theory, so it must be true.
So, they Indians
Indians are a people who are very
differential to authority, right? This
is what's drilled into us through the
education system.
Which is And that's why it's so easy to
mislead Indians. My point is there was
no Aryan invasion or migration. There is
zero evidence of that. Without evidence,
I will not agree to this.
And all the genetic evidence, it it
doesn't stand up to scrutiny. Nothing.
None at all.
Um
So,
there is no evidence of migration. There
is no evidence of invasion. There is no
There is no evidence of a tourism. There
is no evidence of picnic. Nothing.
There is no invasion or evidence of an
alien invasion, also. Nothing at all.
Similarly, right?
It's It's like the ancient aliens
theory. It's It's exactly the same as
that.
So, my point is that none of this
happened. None of this happened.
And let's say some some people migrated,
let's say hypothetically, during the
decline of the IVC.
See, this Indus Valley Civilization,
once again,
we are made to imagine it was some
separate civilization that existed in
the past.
Some mysterious people lived there, and
they disappeared. We have no idea where
they went.
The truth it is is that it is
one of the phases of our history.
The people of the so-called Indus Valley
Civilization were nothing but Indians.
And the larger river in the that time
was the Saraswati, not the Indus to the
Sindhu.
And it was not a separate civilization.
It was Indian civilization.
And all the cultural
traits and characteristics that were
practiced at the time, we still practice
today.
We do.
You don't look it up.
Homework.
And at that time, around 1500 BC,
yeah, you had climate change.
The Saraswati had largely dried up in
the southern
part of her course.
Um when you had a period of drought and
so on.
And this was actually not an isolated
event localized in
in Western India.
At the same time,
you had
the Bronze Age disaster in across the
across the Mediterranean, right?
So, it was something that was that was
happening globally at this around this
time.
So, yeah.
Right, next question.
Vidhi Manyar says, "How did experts
prove that Rigveda is the oldest book,
oldest existing book?"
Well, has any expert proved that?
I would actually say that the experts
are arguing it is not the oldest book.
Let me show you. Proof. Let's find proof
together. Come on.
Okay, let's Google world's oldest
literature and see what happens.
See what experts say.
Uh world's
Oh, man.
Oh, no.
World's oldest
literature. Okay, there we have it.
Let's go to our best source ever,
Wikipedia. Most reliable source ever.
Let's see what it says.
Oldest literature.
Sumerian texts, like Abu Salabikh.
And instructions of Shuruppak.
And the Kesh Temple Hymn.
2600 BC. They're dated perfectly.
Again, the Life of Metjen in Saqqara.
Egyptian. Then Egyptian The Diary of
Merer and Instructions of Hardjedef.
And Sumerian Hymn to Enlil and Enlil and
Ninlil and Debate between Sheep and
Grain.
2400 BC. Code of Urukagina.
Uh 2400 BC Pyramid Texts, Cannibal Hymn.
Nice.
Uh Maxims of Ptahhotep.
Palermo Stone, Egyptian. And
Du-Hena-Nena's Hymns. Autobiography of
Wenamun and South Saqqara Stone. Epic of
Gilgamesh.
Sumerian King List.
Self-Praise of Shulgi. Code of Ur-Nammu.
Satire of the Trades. 2000 BC Coffin
Texts of Egypt and Teachings of King
Merikare.
Uh Lord of Aratta, Lament for Ur.
Akkadian Laws.
Kultepe Texts. Eloquent Peasant. Barutu.
Uh 1600 1650 BC Dialogue between a Man
and His God. Hittite Code of the
Nesilim.
Okay.
What else? Venus Tablet of Ammisaduqa,
whatever it is.
Then if we uh come to perhaps um
Where Where can I find something that
actually
1500 BC, what do we have? What do we
have? What do we have?
Shikuru Shakulu. Tale of Two Brothers.
Yajurveda is 1200 BC, apparently.
Right? I'm sure there is something
before that somewhere, but it's Ah.
1500 BC to 1000 BC, Sanskrit Rigveda.
So, this is your
academic consensus
that the Rigveda was written written
between 1500 BC
to 1000 BC.
So, the experts have done their best to
prove that the Rigveda is not the
world's oldest book.
It's very new. Only 1000 BC.
Nothing. Nothing at all.
You see?
That's not I am going against the river.
I'm swimming upstream.
I'm going against the grain.
I am the one saying that the the Rigveda
is the world's oldest literature. I am
alone saying that. There are other
Indians who say that also. I'm not I'm
not the only person saying that in
India.
But outside of India, everybody laughs
at us. Now, what? You people You people
are all Hindutva wadi idiots.
Your religion has messed up your brains.
Oh, there is so much other literature.
It's all Sumerian. See, if you look at
that list that I gave you,
these are all dead civilizations that
they are extolling.
The only living civilization in all
those lists is Indian civilization.
They are The West is okay with extolling
the the deeds of dead and defeated
civilizations.
But us? No.
So, experts have actually proven
allegedly proven that the Rigveda was
written between 1500 to 1000 BC. That's
it. Closer to 1000 BC than to 1500 BC.
It's nowhere as old as you people
allege. And your Saraswati, it's a myth.
Total myth. Nonsense.
Okay?
So, please be cognizant of this fact.
The world doesn't agree with us.
The world laughs at us when we say that
the Rigveda is the oldest.
What is my understanding? The Rigveda
was written closer to 6000 BC
than to 1500 BC.
Closer to 6000 BC than to 1500 BC. To
understand why, you can look at my old
videos. I have plenty of videos about
that.
Okay, Duryodhana Pathak says, "What was
the importance of war elephants in India
compared to horses?
How did invaders How
were invaders able to tackle our war
elephants?"
So, what was the importance of war
elephants compared to horses?
What is the importance of aircraft
carriers compared to warships?
What's the importance of nuclear
submarines compared to diesel
submarines?
What's the importance of tanks
as compared to armored personnel
carriers? What's the importance of
fighter planes
as compared to long-distance strategic
bombers?
I think if you make these comparisons,
it becomes very clear. What's the
importance of war elephants, right? War
elephants were akin to tanks,
today's tanks.
You shoot at tanks, you lob whatever at
tanks, the tanks are mostly unhurt.
Of course, today we have anti-tank
missiles and all. That's a different
story.
So, eventually, even even against
elephants, they developed various
means of attacking elephants that were
akin to anti-tank missiles today.
So, eleph- elephants were this huge
mobile battle platforms. The elephant
himself was a very scary animal who
could trample the enemy and would not be
hurt
with
conventional weapons, if especially if
he was armored. And from the top of the
elephant, you could, you know, shoot
arrows or use spears or whatever and do
a tremendous amount of harm.
And the first time you see an elephant
coming at you, you
unless you're a trained soldier, your
blood will run cold in in your body.
And if you're riding a horse, your horse
will just turn apart turn and run.
That's the importance of war elephants.
They were like you know, they caused
shock shock and awe in the enemy.
Eventually, invaders also took
elephants.
When we did the treaty 2300
300 years ago between us and the
Seleucid Empire,
uh our emperor gave the Seleucid uh
Seleucid king, Seleucus Nicator, 500 war
elephants
as dowry or something,
allegedly.
Uh and how do you deal with elephants?
Once you get used to how elephants fight
and so on, you can find ways, you know,
long lances and things that will
genuinely hurt elephants and so on. Or
do something that scares elephants and
so on. That's another thing. So,
eventually, you you are able to deal
with every every new thing
once you get used to it.
Amisha Mishra says, "How did Rajputs end
up being confined to the state of
Rajasthan?" Okay.
Rajputs confined to the state of
Rajasthan. Let me ask a question.
We all know who Ravindra Jadeja is,
right?
He's a Rajput. Jadeja. Where is he from?
Where is he from? He's from Saurashtra.
Where is Saurashtra? Have you seen the
map today? Let's go to the map in case
we are not aware of where Saurashtra is.
Um
Okay.
Here is map, yes?
Where is Saurashtra? Saurashtra is the
jaw.
If Gujarat is the face of a person,
Saurashtra is the jaw. You know, this
region, Rajkot, Junagadh, all that,
Jamnagar, Bhavnagar,
where is Porbandar, where Mr. Gandhi was
born?
Yeah, here is Porbandar. And of course,
you have Dwarka here, you have Somnath
here. So this is Saurashtra.
And Mr. Jadeja, Ravindrasinh Jadeja, is
from Saurashtra.
He's a Rajput.
So is
is he from Rajasthan? He's not from
Rajasthan, he's from Gujarat,
Saurashtra.
Um
and once again, if you go to the map,
you know, there are many Rajputs who
don't live in Rajasthan, lots of them
live in Gujarat.
There used to be this region called
Rajputana,
which was Gujarat and Rajasthan
combined.
That's where you had Rajputs, and today
also historic, I mean, the descendants
of those Rajputs, they live across
Rajasthan, Gujarat, even other parts of
India. So it's not correct, I mean, we
are made to believe that Rajasthan is a
state where Rajputs live. Rajasthan,
Rajputs,
the the land of the Rajputs and so on,
but it's not quite true. The Then you to
ask yourself, what do you we mean what
do we mean by this term Rajput?
It comes from the old Sanskrit term
Rajyaputra, which was which is a term
that emerged sometime in the second
millennium AD.
Around 1000 AD, nobody called themselves
Rajput.
And the term did not exist.
Uh but eventually after the Turkic
invasions and occupation of various
parts of India, this term emerged at
some point in time. These people were
called Rajputs or Rajyaputras, which
meant the descendants of the old ruling
families of India.
Apparently, there were 33 ruling
families, and you can look up the list.
The 33 ancient ruling families dating
back to the late Vedic times
who ruled various parts of India. So the
royalty, the old royalty of India, the
old legitimate royalty of India, their
descendants were called the Rajyaputras,
Rajputs. And they were spread across
even UP and other parts of India.
But eventually, we we got this imaginary
idea that only Rajasthan is the land of
Rajputs, which is not true at all.
All right?
Hub says, "Why is only the Gupta empire
credited with the golden age of India
considering we had other powerful and
efficiently organized empires, such as
the Mauryas, the Cholas, the Kushans,
etc. What did the Gupta kings do
differently?" I'm not sure what they did
differently. Why is the Gupta era
considered the golden age of India?
I think during the Maurya Maurya
dynasty era, the Mauryan empire era, we
also had a golden age.
The whole of the subcontinent was
united. We had At the time, we had both
the Dharma,
which was the major thing for some time,
at least during at least during Ashoka's
time.
During one of his descendants' time, he
was all after Jainism. He built like
thousands of
Jain temples and so on. And it's so
Yeah, it was always like that way.
All the all the various
aspects of Dharma were were taken care
of.
And of course, you had a tremendous
efflorescence of culture during the the
the the Maurya era, during the Kushan
era.
Fantastic era. At that time,
uh
the Kushan empire, it encompassed all of
northern India,
much of Central Asia from the
Caspian Sea to the Aral Sea, and all of
present-day so-called
Xinjiang of China.
So Emperor Kanishka,
one of our greatest emperors, he
controlled the trade between the East
and the West.
He obviously
was um
He He obviously was controlling India's
trade with the West, which is Rome at
the time.
But he was also taxing the Chinese and
the Europeans when they were trading
with each other, because he controlled
all the lands in between. It made India
tremendously wealthy.
Tremendously wealthy.
Definitely a golden age.
Right? Kanishka's time. Kanishka was a
very vigorous guy.
He
And his entire strategy, if you think of
it, was a mercantile strategy.
It was a trade It was an It was an
economic strategy to to control the
world's economy
by controlling the right parts of the
world. And that's it, what he did
brilliantly.
Right?
Um and that made India super super
wealthy.
Tremendous amounts of gold were flow was
flowing into India every year
because of the genius of Shri Kanishka.
And he used that to spread India's
culture far and wide.
He Indianized the whole of Eastern Asia.
East of India, everything was
Indianized,
starting with his efforts. Of course,
when it comes to Suvarnabhumi and all,
it started about 1000 years before him
because of the great merchants of
Kalinga, that's a different story. But
China, Korea, Japan, Mongolia, all of
that All of that was Indianized through
Kanishka's efforts.
So Kanishka's age was definitely a
golden age. The Mauryan age was
definitely a golden age. The Gupta era,
no question, it was a golden age,
tremendous outpouring of culture and
tremendous prosperity, tremendous
military power, strength and power, all
of that. Yeah, so that's also a golden
age.
The Cholas, why is that not not a golden
age? Tremendous prosperity once again,
control of so much maritime trade and
whatnot, the conquest of Srivijaya, the
vassalization of the entirety of
Southeast Asia, all the way up to the
Philippines in a in a non-colonial,
non-oppressive way.
All these eras are golden eras. I have
no idea why only only the Gupta era is
considered the the golden era. I am a
huge fan of the Gupta emperors, no
question, but I I would say it's unfair
to consider only the Gupta period to be
a golden period of India.
I would say even the Satavahanas,
that period was a golden period, at
least in the in the central part of
India.
They were very able rulers, the
Satavahanas.
Even the Mahakshatrapas, the Western
Satraps, they brought in a golden era in
India. They they were controlling the
trade between India and Rome through the
great ports in Saurashtra and Western
India. And they made India tremendously
wealthy, and they were great patrons of
culture. I would say all of these eras
were golden eras in their own way.
Right? So I don't agree that only the
Gupta era
was a golden era of India. And I think
this was golden.
We had multiple golden periods in India.
Yajnavalkya says, "Is the conquest and
rule over India by the British falsely
overhyped by the Anglophiles as an
extraordinary event, since similar
things were true and perhaps more so of
the Turkic conquests of various parts of
India. For example, the number of
foreign officials in India during
Aurangzeb's rule was perhaps much less
compared to the then population of
India, and most of the Timurid army may
also likely be composed of
native Indian soldiers, regrettably. The
foreign conquerors who initially
established the Delhi Sultanate and the
Timurid empire in India were from
regions of West Asia or Central Asia,
like Babur from Uzbekistan, uh which
were comparable or less than England in
its in terms of area and population.
So, is the conquest and rule over India
by the British falsely overhyped? To a
very large extent, it is. Now, I'll tell
you
it's it's it's a little subtle.
Understand this.
The British also started just like the
Turks with a toehold somewhere in India.
They first established, I think in 1600
and something, 1610 or something, a
factory in Surat in Western India, in
South Gujarat. And then they also
established something in uh
what eventually became Kolkata, Fort St.
George, whatever the hell it was called.
Um
And eventually, they slowly expanded
over the centuries their their, you
know,
their foothold in India, and eventually
they defeated the Marathas, and then
they ruled India, and they so on. So
they kind of followed the same pattern
that the Mughals did, the Turkic the
Turkic
occupiers of India, the Mughal dynasty.
Even they started with a small foothold
in India. They kind of lost it for a
while to a native Sher Shah Suri.
Well, you will say that Sher Shah Suri
was Afghan, but he was native to the
subcontinent,
right? He was from Gandhara, he was not
from Central many most of them were
actually Indians.
Uh and his successor was a Hindu.
Um Hemu, Hemachandra Vikramaditya, last
Hindu emperor of Delhi.
Um yeah, so
So the Mughals had this, you know,
And the Mughal empire lasted about 300
years or something, that's it. And the
British empire eventually lasted about 2
and 1/2 or 300 years, more or less, in
India.
Um but what was extraordinary about the
British is that they colonized much of
the known world. That is something the
Mughals or the Turks could not do.
So that is what was extraordinary about
the about the British. They surpassed
the Mughals in their brutality
and in their ability to rule over very
large portions of the world and to
coordinate the empire from
London.
That is something they they they
surpassed the Mughals in.
So that certainly is extraordinary, the
extent to which they were able to expand
their empire. The sun never set on the
British empire.
And the crown jewel of the British
empire was obviously India, because
that's where
like 80 90% of the wealth was coming
from, the plunder of India.
Uh so you were right, the examples you
gave are absolutely correct. Uh the the
Mughals, the Turks, also, they did
something actually perhaps initially
better than the than the British.
Uh but eventually, the British surpassed
everybody
by conquering so many parts of the world
and occupying them.
Yajnavalkya says, "Were Pakistan,
Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Malaysia, and
Indonesia Buddhist majority among the
masses, not speaking about rulers,
just before their conversion to Islam?
You seem to be a person who studies
patterns in world history and you have
uncovered a very interesting pattern and
the answer to your question is yes.
So it all starts when it comes to the
Indian subcontinent it starts with
Gandhara
which is now Afghanistan.
Gandhara was mostly Buddhist.
Around that time around a thousand years
before today.
So a thousand years ago
you don't have a single Muslim in
Gandhara.
And today you don't have a single Muslim
in Gandhara.
That's what's happened. So yes, Gandhara
was mainly Buddhist.
Uh Pakistan what is now Pakistan was
then Punjab. Pakistan it it it happened
later.
Uh Pakistan did not what is now Pakistan
did not uh fall to the Turks
at the same time as Gandhara. It took
centuries more for what is now Pakistan
to fall to Gandhara. So not Pakistan
Gandhara 100% which is now Afghanistan
it was essentially
very significantly Buddhist majority at
the time.
Uh when it comes to Malaysia, Indonesia
these
parts of the world
were for the longest time
Hindu kingdoms but around the time they
became Islamized or they or or converted
to Islam they had become
Buddhist
uh cultures.
So there seems to be a correlation
between Buddhism and Islam.
There does.
So regions that there are Buddhist
majority convert very rapidly to Islam
and regions that are that are Hindu
majority fight fight fight fight fight
fight still fight.
That's the pattern you see. Indeed.
What's the reason for that? Yeah well
that's you don't you don't ask me that
question so I'll not go into it.
Okay.
Ah question about the history of science
and physics. Okay.
Rahul Dhuna says why did Einstein win
the Nobel for the photoelectric effect
and not for theories of relativity
special and general relativity which
were most groundbreaking theories of all
time.
Was Einstein wasn't Einstein worthy
enough to have three Nobels
undisputedly?
If you look back at history today
and if you look back at Einstein's
contributions to our understanding of
the universe
how many of his theories deserve the
Nobel Prize? Special relativity 100%.
General relativity it deserves 10 Nobel
Prizes at least one. So that's two.
Um photoelectric effect absolutely it it
brought the quantum world into the into
into the into the mainstream.
The the photon right? The quantum of
light and so on. So three is there. You
have three there.
And then you have Brownian motion.
Again a 1905 paper
which proved that atoms exist.
Until that paper was published people
did not believe in the existence of
atoms.
His work on Brownian motion was
groundbreaking it should have been
awarded a Nobel Prize.
So even if you combine special and
general relativity into just one theory
of relativity that makes it three Nobel
Prizes.
Work that is far better than anything
that has been given being given Nobel
Prizes today.
So Einstein deserved at least three
Nobel Prizes at least three.
And there are
the Nobel Prize is a very controversial
prize there have been lots of
controversy controversies.
For example
E.C.G. Sudarshan
he has been denied the Nobel Prize
multiple times he's no longer alive now.
Uh
electroweak theory
Abdus Salam, Weinberg and Glashow
they were awarded the Nobel Prize for
that electroweak theory.
Their entire work was based on work that
Sudarshan had done as a as a 25 year old
or something.
So you award the Nobel Prize for a
building but the person who who
constructed the foundation you don't
give the prize to that person why?
Then once again this this guy called
Glauber who was awarded the Nobel Prize
in when 2000 something for something
called the P representation which was a
stolen idea of
of Sudarshan which Sudarshan had already
published way before Glauber and Glauber
actually opposed that but then he
realized that
the that Sudarshan's work actually makes
sense. So then he renamed it to the P
representation and today it's called the
Glauber Sudarshan representation.
Even though Sudarshan was the person who
came with it first. So Sudarshan has
been unfairly kept out of the Nobel
Prize
thing
which obviously
right? What about Bose? Not Subhas
Chandra Bose Satyendra Nath Bose.
Nobel Prizes have been given for the
Bose-Einstein condensate and other
things related to the Bose-Einstein
statistics but the person who
who published the work who who
discovered the statistics first was
Bose.
Satyendra Nath Satyendra Nath Bose he
was never given the Nobel Prize.
Nobel Prizes were given to work done on
the basis of his work
but not to Bose himself.
And it should not even be called the
Bose called the Bose-Einstein statistics
it should be called the Bose statistics.
Einstein merely recommended his paper.
He translated the paper into German and
and and submitted it to Annalen der
Physik or something.
And then it was called Bose-Einstein
statistics. It should be called only the
Bose statistics. Einstein had no
contribution in that.
So you have many such controversies in
in the history of physics.
Uh so why did Einstein win for the
photoelectric effect not for other
things? So Einstein won the Nobel Prize
in 1920 21 21 perhaps.
And uh at that time you see the Nobel
Committee is a very conservative.
They don't want to cause controversy
apparently even though they can cause
all kinds of huge controversies and they
want to give the Nobel Prize to work
that is 100% proven and nobody can
question it.
So by that time in 1921 or whenever it
was given the photoelectric effect was
very well proven experimentally. There
was no question about it anymore that's
why they gave it for that.
Um but at that time relativity was still
kind of being proven. In 1919 I think
Eddington and his teams had demonstrated
that light was bent by the sun
as per Einstein's predictions not per as
per Newton's predictions which means
that the Einstein is correct but it was
only until the 1960s and 70s that
Einstein was completely 100% vindicated
and in 2015 even gravitational waves
were were discovered.
Uh
but in 2015 Einstein was no longer alive
even in 1970 he was no longer no longer
no longer alive. So that's why I think
that's why they decided to give it only
for the photoelectric effect and not for
the other things.
He should have won at least three Nobel
Prizes. There have been people who won
more than one Nobel Prize.
Einstein should have won at least three
and and Sudarshan should have won at
least two.
Rahul Dhuna K says why did a paper on
quantum tunneling written way back in
1985 receive the Nobel Prize in 2025? I
think the Nobel Committee has this
unofficial policy today.
That we will not award a Nobel Prize to
a young person.
We will award a Nobel Prize only to
people who are above 80 or 75 or 80
years old. I think or at least above 70.
Nobody who is actively doing research
should be awarded awarded a Nobel Prize
because it will
encourage them too much.
Give it to people who are done.
People who are just waiting for the
knock knock from Yamaraj. Give it to
those people only.
I don't know what the deal is.
I'm sure if you look at statistics
you know let's let's try and Google it.
Can can you find it? Let's see.
Uh physics Nobel Prize
age
physics Nobel Prize
recipients
age
over the years.
Do we have a graph somewhere?
Do we have a graph?
Not chemistry physiology
age when received Nobel Prize.
See as you see
it it's trending upwards but it is not
showing it as as markedly as they should
show it.
I'm not sure anybody has done this
thing.
Physics.
So in 19 what is this? Nobel Prizes
cumulative number of nah.
Anyway my point is that
in the
in the early 19th century
people used to win Nobel Prizes when
when they were in their 20s, 30s, 40s.
The youngest is about 25 Bragg the
younger Bragg if I'm not mistaken.
Crystal diffraction I think yeah.
But today if you look at the average age
of a Nobel Prize winner it's in their
70s and 80s.
So they have
possibly this unofficial policy that
don't give it to young people.
Only give it to people who are done
finished retired who have nothing more
to contribute. I don't know why but
yeah.
No understanding why. They could have
given the Nobel Prize in 1986 itself
for this work because it was
experimental work.
Quantum quantum tunneling of
quintillions of Cooper pairs right? They
could have done it in given this prize
in 1986 itself when those guys were
young.
They would have been motivated to do
more great work.
But they're giving it now when they're
done over the hill. No one I don't
understand I don't understand why.
Why?
The Super says says where whenever there
are two great powers in the world it
makes sense for them to become rivals of
each other then why did ancient Chinese
and ancient Indian empires why were they
not rivals? Then their spheres of of
interest never overlapped.
Never overlapped.
The Thucydides trap occurs only when
there are overlapping areas of interest,
geographical areas of interest, or
economic areas of interest.
That is what causes rivalries.
But if you have two great powers who are
situated far apart
See, today we think of I'll I'll explain
what the problem is. Okay?
And I have to I'll explain how to
reframe our understanding.
See, today we think of India and China
like this.
So So, in in
in the year 100 AD, you had India like
this and China like this. This is what
we imagine.
And we were both great powers, so why
did we not become rivals?
Are bhai, in in 100 AD, China was only
confined to the eastern part of what is
China.
And this entire Xinjiang region, etc.,
was was no man's land or it belonged to
the Tibetans and other people.
So, understand that today's map of the
world is not
the map was not is it doesn't represent
what the situation was like a hundred
thousand, two thousand, five thousand
years ago.
What was China like in 100 AD? Let's
Let's Google that.
Map of China 100 AD. Let's Let's Google
that.
Then you'll understand.
Map of China 100 AD.
What did China look like in 100 AD?
You see how far it was from India?
Those days we had no aircraft, we had no
telecommunications,
no helicopters, no railways.
It took months to come from China to
India.
So, do you understand now? Look, this
was China, so far away from India.
Uh 100 AD.
So, because of this, there were no
overlapping
zones of interest where
two the interest of the two empires
would have collided.
It never happened.
There was always Tibet, there was always
other other territories in between India
and China.
So, today's China doesn't represent the
real China. The real China is far to the
east. All of the territories have been
are are are non-Chinese territories that
have been occupied by China.
Understand that.
The Baron Zemo says, is history itself a
weapon of geopolitics where narratives
are more important than facts. If so, is
India currently winning or losing the
battle of historical narratives
globally?
Napoleon Bonaparte said that history is
a set of lies agreed upon.
History has always been
something you can use to set narratives.
History's always been
from time to time
different set of lies.
Uh not it it also depends on the
cultural context. The West has
weaponized history.
They're the ones who have been spreading
fake histories.
Uh
if you look at Indian records of
history, you will not find fake
histories here.
But history today is a weapon of
geopolitics. For example, today everyone
is taught in India we we had several
questions today about the Aryan
Dravidian theory, Aryan invasion
migration theory, that India is made up
of two
separate distinct races, Aryans and
Dravidians, and Aryans are the evil
oppressors, and Dravidians are the
rightful natives of India.
And we Aryans should go back to central
Asia or something. People believe that.
People believe then because of the
government and which has weaponized the
caste reservations and all, people
believe that they are the true
mulnivasis of India and they have been
oppressed by for thousands of years by
Aryans, and they are not Hindus.
So, this is weaponization of history.
This is This is the
you know, the the perpetuation of fake
narratives.
In India, everyone is guilty of this.
The old history professors from the 20th
century, some many history professors
today, the government of India itself,
and so many other institutions and all
are propagating fake history. The
objective is to divide the nation
further.
The government may be doing it for votes
because you have to win votes, otherwise
you lose the elections. So, continue
this nonsense. Continue these fake
theories.
Right?
And all these theories were were
initiated by the West to divide India.
The British excelled at this divide and
rule policy.
How do you divide and rule? By making
the natives fight among each other. They
should regard each other as enemies so
that we can rule over them as the
benevolent
rulers. Oh, no, don't fight. We will We
will solve your problems. We will We
will mediate in your disputes. First,
we'll create the disputes. We'll make
you fight each other. Then we will be
the peacemakers. So, you will both sides
will see us as the as the good guys who
are trying their best to have peace, who
are civilizing us.
You do that by creating fake history.
Aryan versus Dravidian, these two fake
identities.
Right? And then caste system, that caste
system was a means of oppression.
And so many other things.
So, is India currently winning or losing
the battle of historical narratives
globally? India is not fighting the
the war of
historical narratives. We are not
fighting.
We are not participating. We'll simply
stand and watch and let things happen to
us.
We are nowhere a participant in this
battle of historical narratives.
Maybe individuals are fighting. Indi-
Individuals don't matter.
It's only when people come together
collectively under strong leadership
that something can happen. And we don't
have that strong leadership in India
today.
It doesn't exist.
Our leadership may be doing great work
in
constructing infrastructure
and so on,
taking care of the economy,
um
doing a good job geopolitically,
uh taking care of the military. But when
it comes to narratives, when it comes to
promoting culture, safeguarding culture,
uh making India a better place for
future generations, I am not sure it's a
a great job is being done right now.
Okay, I am done with today's questions.
Let's take some questions from the live
chat. Oh, good god, we have some super
chats today.
Okay, I'll take Please don't take any
more super chats, please, because I'm
going to end the live stream soon. So,
please don't take any more super chats.
Super chats we can take some other time.
Satellite is new member. Satellite, sir,
thank you so much. Appreciate that.
Viju Sai says, during the Vedic period,
Lord Indra was the most prayed to God by
Hindus. Today, we don't pray to Lord
Indra anymore. Why? What happened?
We are so old as a civilization that new
gods come up or new manifestations of
gods came up.
Right? See, other religions are
such short history that nothing has
changed much. They pray pray to the same
gods.
During the Vedic period, Lord Indra was
prayed to, right? The most worshipped
god god by Indians.
During the Vedic times, they had stopped
praying to
a different god, Dyaus Pitr.
The oldest of the Aryan gods.
How much is he mentioned in the Rigveda,
Dyaus Pitr?
The oldest of the Vedic gods, of the
Aryan gods, are Dyaus Pitr and Prithvi
Mata.
Who worships them today? Who worshipped
them even during the Vedic period?
I'm sure there are some references to
them in the Rigveda, etc., but nothing
compared to Shri Indra Lord Indra.
And Lord Indra was the great mighty
warrior god who destroyed Vritra, right?
The great serpent
with his Vajra, which is a hammer and a
thunderbolt in one, combined in one.
But over time, things changed.
New names came in.
The great god who was called Rudra is
now called Shiva.
Right?
And Indra has been relegated to a
political kind of god who sits in a in a
in a parliament kind of thing with
surrounded by other gods and plays
politics.
And he's the god of rain today.
So, you see how how much time has passed
and how much Indian society has evolved.
It's a natural process, evolution of
society, evolution of beliefs. But this
sort of change happens only over
thousands of years. It indicates how old
and ancient our civilization is and how
much things have changed.
So, Indra was regarded as the god of the
of the thunder and rain, and also the
great warrior god.
But maybe Indra
Indra did not give us what we wanted at
some point in time.
Indra
through his lack of benevolence
caused the death of the Saraswati. So,
maybe that's why peo- people stopped
stopped praying to Indra.
Maybe that's the reason. Maybe some
other reason. I'm not sure. But yeah.
Uh okay.
Nikhil Gungal, well, good to see you,
sir. Thank you. Uh could you tell us
something about Jains?
People today treat it as a separate
religion from Hinduism, but shivalingams
are found in temples like Chota Kailash
in in the lower. Festivals and
traditions all overlap. See, sir, I am
not any kind of expert in Jainism.
I am not the right person to ask this
question.
Maybe in the future I can have somebody
who can explain Jain Dharma to us
properly.
I have not studied Jain Dharma.
So, if I say something, I may be
ignorant and I may end up telling you
something that is not correct. So, it is
better that I don't venture into this.
I'm not
I'm not the right person to ask this
question. Sorry, very sorry.
Sonathan says, please throw some lights
on the Pala kingdom. Once again, it's
not something I've studied in detail.
See, this is the thing about history.
See, I have had Dr. Meenakshi Jain on my
podcast many times.
You ask her about something that she has
not researched, she will tell you
straight to your face, this is not my
cup of tea.
History is so vast
that if you ask
if you take a very
prominent historian
and you ask questions about about things
that they've not studied or researched,
they will say, "I don't know."
It's not
part of my my forte.
So, about this I have to say I don't
know much. Pala kingdom, not sure.
Biju Sai wants to ask a geopolitics
question because today let's do
geopolitics in a history session, right?
Arayser, ask me tomorrow.
Okay, you're talking about dissolution
of USSR. That we can consider to be
history. question. Okay, when you said
CIA and all, I said I was like, "Well,
what?"
So, did CIA or deep state have any
contribution to the dissolution of the
USSR? Or the entire credit goes to Mr.
Gorbachev? The entire credit cannot go
to Mr. Gorbachev.
It cannot.
Of course the deep state, of course the
CIA, of course the US had
a significant contribution
to the dissolution of the USSR in a
variety of ways.
The entire credit cannot go to Mr.
Gorbachev. They did squeeze. They did
not let up the squeeze on the USSR in
all kinds of ways. Economic squeeze,
power projection squeeze, naval squeeze,
other squeeze, all of that.
Uh so, the US did have a significant
contribution,
but
probably Gorbachev's contribution was
probably somewhat larger.
Heer Kumar Patel says, "Who Islamized
Indonesia?" Merchants, Arab merchants is
what we what we hear.
That Arab merchants started trading with
Suvarnabhumi with with Indonesia,
Sumatra, and the Yavadvipa and all. And
they settled there and eventually they
spread their religion and that's how it
happened. That's what we're told.
Uh it was not a conquest, it was just
that sort of thing.
What's the origin and impact of
matriarchy?
I'm I belong to a patriarchal
civilization, so I don't know.
I haven't studied matriarchy, sir. I
have no idea.
I understand patriarchy.
I come from a patriarchal culture.
Super male toxic culture.
Okay, Aryan culture. Indian
civilization. We are patriarchal.
We have some minor matriarchal
subcultures in India, so like so like
somewhere in southern India
and somewhere in the far east of India.
But that's not something I understand
very well.
So.
Cinnamon says,
"Why was the concept of a king with a
hereditary lineage ruling his kingdom,
why was this almost wiped out after
World War II?" What's the link?
Well, after World War II you had other
powers who wanted to establish their
primacy.
So, for example, you have something
called the deep state.
Maybe they are part maybe they belong to
certain lineages who want to stay
hidden.
So, if you ask Chamath Palihapitiya,
who is a American businessman of of
of
Sri Lankan origin. If you ask him,
he will say that there are 150 people,
men, who rule the world.
And they are deeply hidden. That's the
deep state, obviously.
Would you like me to show you what I'm
talking about?
Am I talking conspiracy theories? Okay,
let's see.
Chamath Palihapitiya, 150 men.
There's about 150 people who run the
world.
Okay, in a 2017 appearance at the
Stanford Graduate School of Business, he
said that the approximately 150 men
control a majority of the world's health
wealth and power.
This powerful group is not made of tech
entrepreneurs. They operate outside the
public eye to influence global etc. etc.
etc.
Okay?
What is he talking about?
He's talking about the deep state.
Now, these people want to stay hidden so
that they can have even more power.
If you're visible, then you are
accountable. If you're invisible,
you can be the power behind the act what
seems to be the power. And then you have
no accountability, you can do anything
you want.
So, you destroy the hereditary lineages,
you
mediocritize society.
See, when you impose democracy on a
society which used to have the
hereditary system,
kings and emperors, then you are
bringing the standards down.
You're bringing the standards down to
the lowest common denominator
denominator. Democracy is a lowering of
standards. It is the rule of the mob.
It is the rule of the average IQ, not
the highest IQ.
Right?
That way you can rule the whole world.
If you make the whole world mediocre,
if you impose mediocre systems on the
entire world,
if you have mediocre politicians getting
elected who implement mediocre systems,
mediocre policies, mediocre education
systems, then you with your higher
intellect and hidden behind the scenes
can rule the whole world.
That's what they've done.
I I have requested, please don't take
any more super chats. Anyway, I'll take
the
remaining super chats and then
let's end this.
Um Amisha says, "Why have men dominated
history?"
Historically, we have been
hunter-gatherers.
Historically, we have been a
very violent species.
We still are a very violent species.
It's in our DNA.
Now, because of the way the genders are
biologically,
we have different gender roles. Men
are more muscular, larger, stronger.
That's just biological fact, right?
Males.
And this is seen in multiple species
apart from humans. You look at lions,
for example. Males are like way larger
than females.
Um
I suppose it also applies to other
species of mammals and so on. But we'll
talk about humans here. So,
historically, it's been like this that
because of
our society being so violent, because of
our species being so violent, men had to
take
care of all the fighting, war fighting,
and all and decision-making because they
were in the mid of the middle of the war
and everything on fighting on a
on a regular basis. They understood how
what decisions are were necessary for
that. And women's role was to stay at
home, stay away from the violence,
and raise the next generations.
And that is essentially the reason why
male men have dominated history.
Okay?
6P70 Delta says, "Your opinion on
Brezhnev?"
What I can tell you, he was a heavy
heavy smoker.
If you If you hear his speeches, he has
this smoker's cough.
That's how he
His teeth are all tobacco stains stained
and all. I I am sure he was a very heavy
smoker.
Apart from that he that he was okay.
Nothing special. Yeah.
Brezhnev. Brezhnev. Yes, comrade.
Ankita says, "Good evening, Ankita ji.
Some people refer to Europe as a
civilization saying it's an attack on
European civilization due to migration
from Islamic nations.
Does it qualify
Does it Does it um
Does it qualify to be a civilization?
Does it
have the characteristics of a
civilization? I do not agree that Europe
is one civilization.
It's not.
If you look at Europe just 100 years
ago, they had so many little
principalities and states and nations
and kingdoms and duchies and all
fighting each other.
All had very very different ways of
life.
If you look at France 100 years ago, 150
years ago, they had like 15 different
languages, all sounding same but
different languages, different
clothings, different attires, different
ways of life.
The Provençal language
was very different from the French
language.
Significantly different.
Right?
Um
the Langue d'Oc.
If you look at Italy, you had so many
languages.
So, it has all been artificially
subsumed into these big big chunks.
And today they call it European
civilization. If you go back to the
United States of 150, 200 years ago,
the Anglos did not even consider the
Swedes to be white.
They did not like people who had
migrated to the US from Sweden. They did
not consider them to be white people.
They used to complain that they smell
and they are subhuman.
They used to consider the Irish to be
non-white.
You call this a civilization?
This is an artificial idea that they've
come up with recently.
Um it's a racist idea that the whites
Now, they have accepted that Irish are
white and the and the Swedish are also
white. Earlier, it was only the Anglos
who were white.
I do not agree at all that Europe is a
civilization. There is no such thing as
European civilization. There is no such
thing as Western civilization. There may
be something called Russian
civilization, perhaps.
There was something called Greek
civilization. It's dead.
There is no such thing as Western
civilization or European civilization. I
completely disagree with this notion.
Completely.
And I can argue with anybody based on
actual definitions.
Uh I look like
How dare you?
I look like Brezhnev in sunglasses?
I don't look Russian. Is Is Indian, man.
Is not Is not Russian. What do you talk
about, sir?
How can I look Russian? I'm Indian. In
sunglasses.
Okay, let us end on this really funny
note.
I I always enjoy a good joke.
All right, people.
Uh
Okay, I'll I'll end this over here.
Really had fun doing all this. Uh thank
you so much, everybody, for the
questions. I always try to take as as I
Okay, look at this. Look at these evil
people who are saying evil things about
me.
Evil Aryan.
I look like an evil Aryan. How dare you?
How dare you? How dare you?
All right, people. Thank you so much,
everyone. Always fun chatting to you
all. Tomorrow we shall take
um geopolitics questions. It's going to
be a geopolitics super chat live stream.
I look forward to seeing you there. I'm
sure it'll go way past 2 hours.
And I look forward to seeing you in
that. And a lot is happening in the
world geopolitically. So, let's discuss
all of that tomorrow. Afghanistan,
Taliban,
and so much more.
Okay, I look forward to seeing you
tomorrow. Take care. Keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards.
Keep learning.
I'll see you tomorrow. Take care. Good
day. Good night wherever you are.
Until tomorrow. Bye-bye.